Finding Aid for Craig Covey papers, 1987-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Craig Covey papers 1987-2010
Covey, Craig
1 linear foot
9610 Aa 2
Gay rights activist of Ferndale, Mich. Files relating to his involvement with AIDS prevention and gay rights; include minutes of the board and other materials of the Midwest AIDS Prevention Project, 1988-2001; files accumulated from his work with the Michigan Organization for Human Rights; and miscellanea relating to his campaigns for Ferndale City Council in 1995, 1999, 2003, for mayor in 2007, and for Oakland County Commissioner in 2010.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection is the gift of Craig Covey (donor no. 8462 ) and has come to the library in multiple accessions.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Craig Covey was born in Columbus, Ohio in 1957. He began his advocacy work on behalf of gay rights in Ohio in 1981. He founded the Stonewall Union there and then after moving to Michigan in 1985, he became executive director of the Michigan Organization for Human Rights. A resident of Ferndale, Michigan since the late 1980s, Covey has been active in a variety of both gay and community activities. Covey was a long-time member of the Ferndale city council, having served from 1999 to 2008. He had first run unsuccessfully in 1995. In 2007 he was the first openly-gay mayor of any municipality in the state of Michigan. Elected mayor of Ferndale on November 6, 2007, he was sworn into office on January 14, 2008 for a two-year term, succeeding three-term mayor Robert Porter. He was re-elected unopposed in November 2009. In 2010, he ran successfully for the Oakland County Commission in district 25, succeeding Dave Coulter (D-Ferndale).
Besides political activity, Covey was also CEO of the Midwest AIDS Prevention Project (MAPP) and Chief Operating Officer of the Michigan AIDS Coalition, the organization resulting from the merging of MAPP and the Michigan AIDS Fund in 2009.
The Craig Covey collection is arranged into two series: Topical Files and Audio-Visual Materials. The topical files are especially important for their documentation of his work in various education and prevention study programs. These include the Midwest AIDS Prevention Project (MAPP for short) and the Michigan AIDS High Risk Education program. Also of important are files documenting his participation in the political and civic life of Ferndale, both within the gay community and as a member of the city council and as Mayor. There is documentation of his campaign for office and his participation in a gay and lesbian neighborhood association, Friends and Neighbors of Ferndale (FANS for short). The Audio-Visual series is comprised mainly of DVDs relating to gay pride ceremonies and activities.
Subjects:
Covey, Craig.; Elections--Michigan--Ferndale.; Ferndale (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Gay men--Michigan--Ferndale--Political activity.; AIDS (Disease)--Michigan--Prevention.; Michigan Organization for Human Rights.; Midwest AIDS Prevention Project.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Topical Files
  - AIDS miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Articles by and about Craig Covey (Box 1)
  - Campaigns
    - Ferndale city council campaign, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Ferndale city council campaign, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Ferndale city council campaign, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Ferndale mayoralty campaign, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Oakland County Commissioner, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Ferndale (various issues) clippings (Box 1)
  - Friends and Neighbors of Ferndale (FANS, a gay and lesbian neighborhood association), 1998-2000, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Hate mail (Box 1)
  - Human Rights Ordinance, Ferndale, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Lesbian A-Sisters (organization to improve quality of life for lesbians, disabled or with debilitating health concerns) (Box 1)
  - Medical marihuana (Box 1)
  - Michigan AIDS High Risk Education programs, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Organization for Human Rights (Box 1)
  - Midwest AIDS Prevention Project (MAPP), 1987-2001, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Villaire, Richard (officer and board member of MAPP) (Box 1)
- Audio-Visual Material
  - Photographs and other visuals (Box 1)
  - MOHR Annual Meeting, November 1985, DVD; 0:59:32 (Box 1)
  - AIDS Awareness & Education, MGTV: In Depth Program, taped 1-26-1998, VHS videotape; 57:43 min. (Box 1)
  - You Can Fight City Hall (Video Impact), 2006, DVD (Box 1)
  - Pride Commitment Ceremony, 2006 5-3-2006, DVD; 29 min. (Box 1)
  - Pride Fest 2007 Ferndale Mi., 5 DVDs (Box 1)
  - Craig Covey on WXYT radio program, November 1990, 1 audio cassette; 20 min. (Box 1)